Guide to the Maurice Rea Davie Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Maurice Rea Davie Papers
1914-1975
MS 1359
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
(8 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence of Maurice Rea Davie, primarily with Albert G. Keller, writings, subject files, and photographs.
Davie, Maurice R. (Maurice Rea), 1893-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Albert J. Reiss, Jr., 1978; Douglas Davie, 1990; and transferred from YRG 37-V, 1994.
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of correspondence and printed matter sent by the National Institute of Immigrant Welfare to Maurice R. Davie, a member of the Institute's Board of Directors. Most of the letters concern either requests for Davie to speak, or such routine business matters as committee meetings, dues, and financial problems. Professor Albert. J. Reiss, Jr., of the Yale Sociology Department, gave these papers to the Manuscripts and Archives Department in April 1978.
Biographical / Historical
Maurice Rea Davie was born in Toronto, Canada, on January 22, 1893. He received his A.B. (1915), A.M. (1917), and Ph.D. (1918) from Yale University. Davie was a member of the sociology department at Yale from 1921 until his death in November 1964. Among his areas of speciality were child welfare, immigration, and William Graham Sumner.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Emigration and immigration; Sociology; United States -- Emigration and immigration; Sociologists; Davie, Maurice R. (Maurice Rea), 1893-1964; Keller, Albert Galloway, 1874-1956; Sumner, William Graham, 1840-1910; National Institute of Immigrant Welfare; Yale University. Institute of Human Relations
- Inventory, 1935-1939; 0.25; (1 box)
  - National Institute of Immigrant Welfare
    - Correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Publications, reports, minutes, miscellaneous printed matter, 1935-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1914-1975, undated; Accession 1992-M-042; 5.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1992 Apr
  Received from: Douglas Davie, 1990 Dec 20
  - Correspondence
    - Family, 1961-1964, undated (Box 1)
    - General, 1923-1964, undated (Box 1)
    - Keller, Albert G., 1914-1956, undated (Box 1)
    - Keller, Albert G.: Memoriam written by Maurice R. Davie with correspondence, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Keller, Deane, 1951-1957 (Box 1)
  - Subject files
    - American Historical Association, 1939-1940 (Box 2)
    - American Immigration Conference, 1955 (Box 2)
    - American Jewish Committee, 1940 (Box 2)
    - American Jewish Committee. Research Institute on Peace and Post-War Problems, 1941 (Box 2)
    - American Jewish Committee: "Report on the Polls on Anti-Semitism", 1940 (Box 2)
    - American Jewish Year Book: "Immigration and Refugee Aid", 1947 (Box 2)
    - American Sociological Association, 1940-1975 (Box 2)
    - American Sociological Association: Certificate, 1959 (Box 2)
    - American Sociological Review: Index, 1950-1955 (Box 2)
    - Army pamphlet tables, 1940s (Box 2)
    - Book reviews by Maurice R. Davie, 1924-1961 (Box 2)
    - Civil rights, 1930s-1960s (Box 2)
    - Committee for Study of Recent Immigration from Europe, 1932-1944 (Box 2)
    - Davie, Maurice R.: Curriculum vitae, 1920s-1960 (Box 2)
    - Financial, 1918, 1921, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Graduate students, 1930-1939 (Box 2)
    - Hiking club, 1938-1941, undated (Box 2)
    - Jamaica, 1956-1957, undated (Box 2)
    - Italy, 1958-1961 (Box 2)
    - Marks, Percy, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Miller, John: Biochemistry, 1961, undated (Box 2)
    - New Haven Social Workers Club, 1940 (Box 2)
    - New Haven State Teachers College, 1939-1940 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1936, 1944-1950, 1962, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1940s-1960s, undated (Box 2)
    - Princeton Bicentennial Conference: The Evolution of Social Institutions in America, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Printed material, 1930, 1938, 1961-1963, undated (Box 2)
    - Programs, invitations, 1936-1941, 1950, undated (Box 2)
    - Publishers
      - American Book Company, 1939-1942 (Box 2)
      - Appleton-Century, 1925-1927 (Box 2)
      - Ginn and Company, 1940 (Box 2)
      - Harper and Brothers, 1946-1957 (Box 2)
      - John Wiley and Sons, Inc., 1927-1958 (Box 2)
      - McGraw-Hill, 1927-1955 (Box 2)
      - MacMillan Company, 1927-1953 (Box 2)
      - Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    - Refugee study, 1943-1946 (Box 2)
    - Refugee study, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Refugee study, 1946-1948 (Box 3)
    - Refugee study. Physicians: Division of Statistics, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Research grant application: James S. Davie, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Retirement, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Science of Society. Sumner-Keller: Correspondence, 1924-1927 (Box 3)
    - Seminario sui Problemi di Sociologia Industriale, Firenze, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Sumner, William Graham: Essays of, 1918-1935 (Box 3)
    - Sumner Club Bulletin: Report, 1947 (Box 3)
    - Travel, 1958, undated (Box 3)
    - Unsorted papers, 1920s-1940s (Box 3)
    - Welcome Hall: Study of, 1929-1938 (Box 3)
    - Yale College: 1915 Class Book, 1951-1955, 1962, undated (Box 3)
    - Yale: printed material, 1961-1963, undated (Box 3)
    - Yale University Press, 1930-1957 (Box 3)
  - Writings files
    - "Adjustment of Refugees to American Life" for Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1948 (Box 3)
    - "American Negro in Industry", 1943 (Box 3)
    - Evolution of War, 1924-1939 (Box 3)
    - "Folkways" for Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 1931 (Box 3)
    - "Immigration and Migration" for Encyclopedia Americana, 1960 (Box 3)
    - "Immigrants from Axis Conquered Countries" for Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1942 (Box 3)
    - "Immigration": Revision for F.F.B. textbook, 1925, undated (Box 3)
    - "Incomes and Living Costs of a University Faculty": Background material, 1931 (Box 3)
    - "Is America Becoming Feminized?", undated (Box 3)
    - Italian translations, 1959, undated (Box 3)
    - Keller, Albert G: Articles by Maurice R. Davie, 1957 (Box 3)
    - "Minorities, a Challenge to American Democracy", undated (Box 3)
    - "The Negro and The War": Radio talk, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Negroes in American Society, 1939, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Negroes in American Society: Reviews, 1949 (Box 3)
    - "On Motoring in Europe", 1938-1939 (Box 3)
    - "Our Newest Americans" for Survey Graphic, 1946 (Box 4)
    - "Our Vanishing Minorities", 1944 (Box 4)
    - "Pattern of Urban Growth", 1935-1942 (Box 4)
    - "Pattern of Urban Growth": Ecological study of New Haven, 1938,undated (Box 4)
    - "Percy Marks, Writer and Teacher" for Yale University Library Gazette, 1963 (Box 4)
    - "Problems of City Life", 1931-1949 (Box 4)
    - "Propinquity and Marriage", 1938-1939 (Box 4)
    - "Public Social Service" for Collier's Year Book, undated (Box 4)
    - "Recent Refugee Immigration from Europe", 1947 (Box 4)
    - "The Refugee Immigrant in the U.S.": Public affairs pamphlet, 1945 (Box 4)
    - "Refugees in America", 1947 (Box 4)
    - "Refugees in America": Notices, 1947 (Box 4)
    - "Shall We Change Our Immigration Policy?": Manuscript on U.S. immigration policy, 1946 (Box 4)
    - "Social Aspects of Mental Hygiene" with an introduction by Maurice R. Davie, 1923 (Box 4)
    - "Social Aspects of Psychiatry", 1938 (Box 4)
    - "A Sociological Approach to Study of Nationality Groups in the U.S.", 1940-1941 (Box 4)
    - "Sumner" for Encyclopedia Americana, 1963, undated (Box 4)
    - "William Graham Sumner" for Encyclopedia Britannica, undated (Box 4)
    - "Theory and Practice in Social Science", 1941 (Box 4)
    - "What About Immigration After the War?": Army pamphlet draft, undated (Box 4)
    - "What Shall We Do About Immigration?" for Historical Service Board, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
    - "When Peoples Move", 1949 (Box 4)
    - World Immigration: Correspondence, 1934-1950 (Box 4)
    - Copies of articles by Maurice R. Davie, 1917-1949, undated (Box 4)
  - Writings of others
    - "The Teaching of Sociology in American Colleges" by Kennedy and Reeves (Box 4)
  - William Graham Sumner booklet
    - Notes (Box 5)
    - Draft [pp. 1-25] (Box 5)
    - Draft [pp. 26-51] (Box 5)
    - Draft [pp. 52-76] (Box 5)
    - Thomas Y. Crowell Co., publisher of W.G. Sumner booklet: Correspondence, 1960-1963, undated (Box 5)
    - Major Contributors to Social Science: William Graham Sumner, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
- Additional Material, 1929-1948, undated; Accession 1995-M-216; .5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Diane E. Kaplan 1994 Aug
  Transferred from: YRG 37-V, 1994 Aug 26
  - Institute of Human Relations
    - General, 1929-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - Notes on budget, 1935-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Williams, Phyllis H.
    - General, 1935-1948 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - "Human Reactions to Relief", 1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)